Guide to the Dismal Swamp Land Company records RL.10175
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dismal Swamp Land Company records
circa 1660s-1860s, bulk 1810-1879
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Washington, George, 1732-1799
Walker, Thomas, 1715-1794
Meade, R.K. (Richard Kidder), 1803-1862
RL.10175
4 Linear Feet
Collection comprised of 9 boxes of company records and 5 ledgers of organizational material of the Dismal Swamp Land Company, a shingle production company in existence between 1763-1879. Letter books, receipts spanning the entirety of the company's existence, and legal documents make up the bulk of the collection.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Dismal Swamp Land Company records consist of company records spanning the 17th-19th centuries, with the bulk falling in the mid-to-late 19th century. The majority of records consist of financial documentation, including receipts for the purchase of equipment by the Company and numerous receipts for customers detailing quantities and prices of shingles purchased. Monthly ledgers and an account book are also present. The records include legal documents surrounding surveys of the Dismal Swamp, indentures, wills, and several powers of attorney for shareholder meetings. Incoming correspondence intended for the Company's presidents, mainly from employees and shareholders, makes up the majority of the Correspondence series.
Biographical / Historical
The Dismal Swamp Land Company was founded by George Washington, Thomas Walker, William Nelson, Thomas Nelson, Robert Burwell, John Robinson, Fielding Lewis, Anthony Bacon, John Lyme, Samuel Gist, Robert Tucker, and William Waters. The number of shareholders grew as original owners divested their interests and family inherited stakes. The Company operated between 1763-1879 and was originally interested in agricultural pursuits (including rice cultivation), but the sale of cypress shingles and staves proved more profitable. The company went under as a result of post-Civil War economic conditions and concurrent decrease in the shingle trade.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Dismal Swamp Land Company Records was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1939.
Arrangement
Materials arranged by topic, and then by date.
Dismal Swamp (N.C. and Va.); Dismal Swamp Canal (N.C. and Va.) -- History -- 19th century; Dismal Swamp Canal (N.C. and Va.) -- History -- 19th century; Land companies -- United States; Lumber trade -- Virginia; Shingle industry -- Virginia; Swamps -- Virginia; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Walker, Thomas, 1715-1794; Meade, R.K. (Richard Kidder), 1803-1862
- Financial, 1763 -1879 and undated; 1 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  Financial records of the Dismal Swamp Land Company, including bills of sale, monthly ledgers, insurance certificates, and dividends awarded to stockholders. A substantial portion of the series consists of receipts of payment to the company and its payments to various stockholders, vendors, and legal courts.
  - Early shareholder lists, 1764-1811; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1763-1829 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Account book, 1795; 1 folders Also includes letter book dating from 1812-1813. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter book, 1812-1843 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1830-1834, 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Additional receipts, 1830-1835; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1835-1836, 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Account book, 1837; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1837-1838, 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Additional receipts, 1836-1838; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1839, 1 folders (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Additional receipts, 1839; 1 folders (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1840-1843, 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 14, Folder 13, Folder 15)
  - Additional receipts, 1840-1843; 1 folders (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1844-1848, 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 18, Folder 17)
  - 1848-1849, 1 folders (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Additional receipts, 1843-1849; 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 20, Folder 21)
  - 1850-1860, 3 folders (Box 3, Folder 23, Folder 22, Folder 24)
  - Additional receipts, 1850-January 1851, 1 folders (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Additional receipts, January 1851-July 1852, 1 folders (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Additional receipts, August 1852-1859, 1 folders (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1860-1870, 4 folders (Box 4, Folder 29, Folder 30, Folder 28, Folder 31)
  - Additional receipts, 1860-1869; 3 folders (Box 4, Folder 32, Folder 33, Folder 34)
  - Additional receipts, 1869-1870; 1 folders (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - 1870-1879, 5 folders (Box 5, Folder 38, Folder 39, Folder 36, Folder 37, Folder 40)
  - Additional receipts, 1870-1879; 1 folders (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Undated, 1 folders (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - 1779-1810 (Box 9, Oversize-folder 1)
  - 1836-1837 (Box 9, Oversize-folder 2)
  - 1838-1839 (Box 9, Oversize-folder 3)
- Legal, 1665-1879 and undated
  Legal papers of the Dismal Swamp Land Company. Includes separate folders related to Powers of Attorney for annual meetings and last wills and testaments for investors in the Company. Series also includes indentures, court cases filed by and against the Company, and legal guardian documentation.
  - 1665-1832, 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - 1833-1855, 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - 1856-1879 and undated, undated; 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Wills, 1749-1805; 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Wills, 1805-1866; 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Powers of attorney, 1825-1836; 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Powers of attorney, 1837-1845; 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Powers of attorney, 1846-1871; 1 folders (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - 1792-1816 (Box 9, Oversize-folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1688-1879 and undated
  - 1688-1791, 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - 1792-1813, 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - 1816-1819, 3 folders (Box 7, Folder 55, Folder 54, Folder 53)
  - 1820-1851, 2 folders (Box 7, Folder 56, Folder 57)
  - 1853-1870, 3 folders (Box 8, Folder 58, Folder 59, Folder 60)
  - 1871-1879 and undated, 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 61, Folder 62)
- Miscellaneous, 1763-1879
  - Photocopies, 1794- circa 1855, 1 folders (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Other--family tree, Martha Fort (Box 9, Oversize-folder 5)
- Ledgers, 5 items
  - M:911 (Volume M:911)
  - M:912 (Volume M:912)
  - M:913 (Volume M:913)
  - M:914 (Volume M:914)
  - S:910 (Volume S:910)